Fletcher School Records UA015
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
- Fletcher program theses, 1981 -- 2015; UA015.012; 286 Digital Object(s); 1 Volumes
  - Colaborar - Ñamba'apo OÑondivepa - Collaboration: An Analysis of Inter-Agency Collaborations in Developmental Technical Assistance in Paraguay, 2005; UA015.012.DO.00093; Lindenbaum, Stephanie K
    Submitted in partial fulfillment of the degree Master of Arts in Law and Diplomacy at the Fletcher School of Law and Diplomacy. Abstract: The United States Peace Corps has paired private American citizens with communities in developing countries for over forty years, yet it suffers a crisis of personality. Created ostensibly for the purpose of aiding developing world peoples, it is frequently criticized for providing a richer and more meaningful experience for the volunteers themselves than for their host communities. This paper examines Peace Corps' history and organizational culture as compared with the United States Agency for International Development, or USAID. With the Millennium Challenge Account threatening to alter the way in which USAID conducts development assistance programs abroad, it appears that USAID, like Peace Corps, should perhaps reevaluate its operations, and consider collaborating with other US Government agencies. Through two case studies of Peace Corps Volunteers in Paraguay, this paper looks at how they have worked on USAID-funded projects, and how this collaborative effort may be an attractive model for the future.
    MALD thesis; Civil Society; Community development; Development Economics; Economic Development; International agencies; Non-governmental organizations
  - Evaluating Transitional Justice Mechanismsí Effect on Reconciliation: Case Study Sierra Leone, 2005; UA015.012.DO.00094; Loizou, Elaina
    Submitted in partial fulfillment of the degree Master of Arts in Law and Diplomacy at the Fletcher School of Law and Diplomacy. Abstract: Utilizes institutional theory and in-country empirical field research to evaluate to what degree transitional justice mechanisms (both truth & reconciliation commissions and international courts) are achieving their goal of contributing to national reconciliation in post conflict countries. Sierra Leone is studied in depth, but the methodology and policy recommendations are applicable broadly to aid scholars and practitioners in the field of transitional justice.
    MALD thesis; International law; Reconciliation
  - Post-Conflict Democratization and Depoliticizing of Conflicting Identities: Constitutional Transformation in Bosnia and Herzegovina, 2005; UA015.012.DO.00095; Marjanovic, Maja
    Submitted in partial fulfillment of the degree Master of Arts in Law and Diplomacy at the Fletcher School of Law and Diplomacy. Abstract: In situations of identity-based conflicts and their post-conflict transformation, what ought to occur is the depoliticizing of conflicting identities because those should not be enshrined legally as a sole political reality. The depoliticizing of conflicting identities, and consequently transformation of conflict, will take place through the societal re-conceptualizing of political identity and broadening of the concept of power through redefining the cultural and political discourse. In order to demonstrate the feasibility of depoliticizing group identities, the study utilizes the case of Bosnia and Herzegovina. I propose for Bosnia to undertake the re-making of its constitution as an initial step toward depoliticizing wartime identities. The recommendation of this study is for the population to be actively engaged in constitutional change through popular participation which will take place in a two stage process, civic education and popular consultation.
    MALD thesis; Civil Society; Conflict Management; Ethnic relations; Peace; Political rights
  - How Marketing Mumbo Jumbo Can Help Poor Countries Grow: The Case of 100% Columbian Coffee, 2005; UA015.012.DO.00096; Marti, Rafael
    Submitted in partial fulfillment of the degree Master of Arts in Law and Diplomacy at the Fletcher School of Law and Diplomacy. Abstract: This work starts with an overview of the consequences of falling prices in manufactures for developing countries and the role marketing and country branding can play in promoting exports to high income countries, where differentiated products are sold with high margins. To understand how branding works, the second chapter presents a summary of scientific findings regarding the psychological dimension of branding, focusing on the role emotions play; it also analyses the main traits of today's branding. Building upon this framework, chapters III and IV, review the case of the 100% Colombian Coffee campaign, and examine its brand equity, history, and recent development. As a conclusion, some guidelines are given to poor countries in order to take advantage of marketing techniques when exporting to the US and Europe.
    MALD thesis; Communications; Development Economics; Economic Development; Globalization; Sustainable Development; Management; Business
  - Revealed Preferences in US Bilateral Aid, 1960-2000, 2005; UA015.012.DO.00097; Mazzotta, Ben
    Submitted in partial fulfillment of the degree Master of Arts in Law and Diplomacy at the Fletcher School of Law and Diplomacy. Abstract: This paper proposes and evaluates determinants of US bilateral foreign aid. An earlier cross-country comparison of donors (Alesina and Dollar, 1998) suggested two determinants that offer limited explanatory power as determinants of bilateral aid flows: colonial relationships and political ties. As the US has no colonial relationships, the former makes no prediction of US bilateral aid spending. The latter is measured by proxy in Alesina and Dollar's work, through the correlation of UN votes between donor and recipient. As they acknowledge, this measure potentially suffers from reverse causality (Alesina and Dollar, 1998). I offer four hypotheses for determinants of US bilateral aid spending: 1. Trade ties with the recipient country. 2. Operations of the US military, 3. Political events in the recipient country, and 4. Economic events in the recipient country, In order to test these hypotheses, I use data from the USAID Green Book, which specifies types of spending including military and economic assistance, and modalities of spending including loans and grants (USAID 2002). The Green Book data are the dependent variables in cross-sectional regressions on indicators of governments political leanings and democratic performance, indicators of economic health, the presence of a named US military operation, and indicators of economic relationships with the US. Indicators of governments' political leanings come from the World Bank's Database of Political Institutions. Democratic performance comes from the Polity variable in the Polity IV dataset from the University of Maryland's Integrated Network for Societal Conflict Research. Indicators of economic health are found in the Penn World Table, from the University of Pennsylvania's Center for International Comparisons. The list of named US military operations comes from Global Security, a Washington think tank. The closeness of economic ties with the US is measured with the IMF's Direction of Trade Statistics historic series. The specific composition of the variables and controls is listed below in the section 'Data'. The regressions in Tables 1 to 4 assess the revealed preferences of the US foreign aid programs in aggregate. Washington allocates bilateral aid to countries that are trading partners, that are poorer, that are secular, and that have strong nationalist executive parties. US bilateral aid rises in response to adverse economic shocks. US bilateral aid falls in real per capita terms over time. Economic assistance, and specifically USAID spending, is highest when centrists and nationalists control the executive branch. Economic assistance shies away from countries with major religious parties. Contrary to popular opinion, Washington (on an intercontinental, decades-long scale) does not lavish aid on right-wing governments, nor does it systematically undermine the left.
    MALD thesis; Civil Society; Comparative government; Development Economics; Diplomatics; Economic assistance; Economic Development; Economic policy; International Relations; National security; Political rights; Political science; Regional planning; War; World politics
  - China's Banking System and How Citibank Can Capitalize on its Liberalization, 2005; UA015.012.DO.00098; McGeehan, Kevin
    Submitted in partial fulfillment of the degree Master of Arts in Law and Diplomacy at the Fletcher School of Law and Diplomacy. Abstract: The potential that China's economy holds as it moves to a more liberal market economy is limitless, and Western firms are eager to become the first movers in their industries to take advantage of this promise. Western banks are no exception. Chinese regulations have historically limited the operations of foreign banks, but with the entry of China into the World Trade Organization, that is all slated to change - in theory. Geographic limitations for foreign banks are to be lifted by December 2006, along with a host of other restrictions that have retarded the growth of these Western banks and the Chinese banking sector as a whole. Progress on these liberalizations has been slow, however, and Chinese regulators have even put other limitations in place that will hurt competition in the long run. This is far from the only problem facing the Chinese banking sector. Decades of policy lending have saddled the four state-owned banks with an unhealthy level of non-performing loans from state-owned enterprises. Asset management companies have been created to manage these NPLs, but the situation is far from stable. A lack of corporate governance has also created an environment where management of banks is opaque and corruption widespread. The risks inherent in this industry are great. In this environment then, what is Citigroup's best method of operation? Once reentry to the market was allowed, Citigroup pushed hard to maintain its control in China by avoiding joint ventures and operating independently. As this strategy stalled and its competitors gained the upper hand in the country, Citibank changed its approach to embrace joint ventures and entertain the idea of buying into the state bank system. Is this the right approach? Citibank is right to pursue joint ventures at this time, especially because building its own structures in China would be cost-prohibitive and too slow to develop. At the same time, the bank must be careful with whom it associates in China. The possibility of corruption or mismanagement is still significant with regard to partnerships with state-owned banks. It also cannot expand its offerings too quickly or expose itself to too much risk. It should use its government connections to speed up the deregulation process, plan for the time when this becomes a reality, and train native Chinese workers in Western bank practices. Citibank is currently not the most successful foreign bank in China; that title belongs to HSBC. A combination of prudent growth and innovative service upgrades should allow Citibank to compete with and eventually overtake its rival in this burgeoning market.
    MALD thesis; Business; Government business enterprises; Investments, Foreign; Privatization
  - Toward a More Sustainable Democracy: Public Participation in Justice Sector Reform, 2005; UA015.012.DO.00099; Mcilvain, Ashley
    Submitted in partial fulfillment of the degree Master of Arts in Law and Diplomacy at the Fletcher School of Law and Diplomacy. Abstract: In both researching and participating in the process of planning and implementing rule of law reforms, I saw several trends that seemed to indicate a need for change. It is these themes that have guided the development of this paper and my hopes of its application in future rule of law promotion efforts. The experience of donors and practitioners in countries around the world in recent years has illustrated that: Reforms led by international donors do not always coincide with local priorities or needs; Institutional reforms often unravel after the international community's departure due to a lack of domestic capacity or support; The broader public is often excluded from and disillusioned with the reform process; Reforms do not always adequately address the need to develop a participatory tradition or the existing public cynicism about democratic participation in government. Certainly, these are themes already raised by a wide range of scholars and practitioners. Current wisdom now dictates that: Development of both the process and content of reforms should include local input and be subject to local control; Local capacity-building should be a priority in the reform process from the outset; Civic education is a necessary antecedent to effective democratic participation; The reform process itself is equally as important as its final product in determining the legitimacy of the institutions it creates. Even among those that agree with these points, the question remains as to how these goals can be most effectively accomplished. The research and program analysis I present here examines how public participation in rule of law reform may complement existing initiatives to help achieve these goals. Such an approach is certainly not immune to critique. Many international donors, state governments and publics alike are skeptical about either the value or efficacy of public participation in government reform and work, not least because it remains a new field of exploration with little empirical evidence to support it. There is, however, much anecdotal evidence of state and local reforms of the police and judiciary where public involvement was a key component in building public trust in the reform process and the government, increasing the legitimacy of the police and judiciary, and improving the accountability and effectiveness of these institutions. Through the analysis and examples included in this study, I have attempted to provide an objective assessment of the potential benefits and drawbacks of a participatory approach, raising issues relevant to international and state actors considering whether to integrate public participation in their particular reforms. I have also sought to address how civic education and gradual public engagement may be used to reduce public cynicism and reticence toward democratic participation. In vetting the rationale, opportunities and practical challenges to such participation, it is my hope that the initiatives discussed here may be successfully integrated into current and future reform programs to provide a more holistic approach to rule of law promotion in new democracies.
    MALD thesis; Civil law; Comparative government; Human rights; International agencies; International law; Intervention (International law); Law reform; Political rights; Public policy; Social Policy; World politics
  - Reducing Refugee Rights? A comparative analysis of shifting refugee policy and practice in Mozambique and Guinea, 2005; UA015.012.DO.00100; Mecagni, Anna Lucia
    Submitted in partial fulfillment of the degree Master of Arts in Law and Diplomacy at the Fletcher School of Law and Diplomacy. Abstract: There is a stark contrast between the ever expanding body of international law which addresses the protection of refugees and the imposition of increased restrictions due to stringent state policies and practices which refugees face in host countries. Expanding refugee protection at the international level takes the form of new covenants and declarations, increasing numbers of signatories on and ratifications of existing instruments, and regional agreements between groups of states. On the other hand, policies and practices of refugee hosting governments have sometimes led to a curbing of refugees' rights. Some countries, which at one time had quite friendly approaches toward refugees, have scaled back their liberal practices and reduced the rights afforded to refugees. This thesis aims to better understand the factors that are leading host countries to shift their policies and practices toward refugees from liberal to stringent. The paper will focus on developing countries, particularly in Africa, which have signed onto refugee rights instruments and have, at one time, had relatively liberal stances toward acceptance and treatment of refugees. Through an exploration of two case studies - Guinea and Mozambique - the drive behind the states' shift from liberal policies and practices, which limit the rights of refugees within their borders, will be explored. In short, this paper addresses the research question: what are the main factors which drive states to shift from liberal to stringent policies and practices towards refugees?
    MALD thesis; Forced migration; Human rights; International Relations; National security; Political rights; Refugees; Security, International
  - Diplomatic Investments, 2005; UA015.012.DO.00101; Molloy, Michael Sean
    Submitted in partial fulfillment of the degree Master of Arts in Law and Diplomacy at the Fletcher School of Law and Diplomacy. Abstract: This paper argues that the aims of American and Chinese commercial policies promoting foreign direct investment (FDI) have been successfully aligned with the effects of their implementation; private sector interests have complemented and reinforced the commercial policy intentions of both nations to encourage development while at the same time helping to promote the peaceful resolution of bilateral tensions. This successful alignment of governmental policies and business interests has given rise to diplomatic investments, which continue to play a role in defining opportunities for stable and productive mutual gains for both countries. The study begins with an overview of the current state of economic integration between the U.S. and China, identifying some of the key benefits which the implementation of diplomatic investments have brought to the bilateral relationship in terms of economic development and political stabilization. This dual advantage of effectively implemented pro-FDI commercial policies is further elaborated on through a blending of both realism and complex interdependence frameworks; a combination of both theories is used as a complementary means for analyzing this dynamic. A brief historical account of commercial policies is then provided in an attempt to demonstrate a positive correlation between pro-FDI policy implementation and non-violent conflict on the one hand, and instances of armed conflict during periods devoid of such policy initiatives on the other. A statistical analysis is next undertaken to demonstrate how the FDI policy implementation process has created a framework for cooperation which enables private sector interests to naturally promote a more stable and productive framework for economic interdependence. The changes brought about by increased economic integration have made both countries increasingly vulnerable to a prolonged cessation of bilateral commercial activity, further reinforcing both national and private sector interests in building a stronger structure for the peaceful resolution of conflict. These theoretical, historical, and statistical interpretations of the pro-FDI policymaking process are then applied to three case studies in which recent potentially violent crisis situations were peacefully resolved. Explanations for the peaceful resolutions of the Taiwan Strait Crisis of March, 1996, the Chinese Embassy bombing in Belgrade in May, 1999, and the EP-3 Incident of April, 2001 would all be incomplete without an appreciation for the pacifying role played by government commercial policies and the market forces they helped to unleash through the promotion of foreign investments. Expert testimonies regarding each case are included to demonstrate that policymakers, academics, and business leaders alike recognize the importance of FDI in promoting cooperative resolutions to the geopolitical conflicts in question. The paper concludes by stating that the successful management of the bilateral commercial policymaking process contributes to peaceful, non-violent diplomatic relations between the U.S. and China because economic security for both countries has become increasingly tied to the continuance of structurally interdependent trade and investment. As long as economic growth is maintained and both countries continue to benefit from FDI exchanges, these current trends are likely to continue.
    MALD thesis; Investments, Foreign
  - The Dual Imperative to Enhance National Security and Foster Human Rights: The United Nations and the Adoption of Resolution 1373, 2005; UA015.012.DO.00102; Morarji, Maitri
    Submitted in partial fulfillment of the degree Master of Arts in Law and Diplomacy at the Fletcher School of Law and Diplomacy. Abstract: On September 28th, 2001, the United Nations (hereafter, the UN) Security Council unanimously adopted Resolution 1373, through which it codified abstract and specific rules pertaining to terrorism which are obligatory and binding on all member states. While mainstream discourse has pointed to the opportunities provided by Resolution 1373 to build a consistent and coherent global anti-terrorism regime, international human rights advocates have raised grave concerns over its sanctioning of human rights violations by state authorities under the guise of countering terrorism. This dually descriptive and prescriptive paper will investigate the impact of Resolution 1373 on the global human rights regime, its actors, and its institutions by exploring the following three questions: 1) Does the mandate of UN Security Council Resolution 1373 pose a threat to the international human rights regime?; 2) What precedent does the Security Council's legislative act set?; and, 3) Do the implementation and enforcement mechanisms, and obligations contained within Resolution 1373 condone state behavior that is ultimately detrimental to states' citizens? By examining the philosophical, structural, and functional components, as well as the political factors that led to the establishment of Resolution 1373, the study proposes that the resolution poses a threat to the international human rights regime by providing states with the façade of UN sanction to implement sweeping anti-terrorism measures. Albeit lofty in its objective to build a global standard to assist states in taking practical measures to prevent the scourge of terrorism both domestically and internationally, the Security Council and the institutions of Resolution 1373 lack the current capacity to monitor states' compliance in a manner that recognizes and reinforces global human rights norms. Through the adoption of Resolution 1373, the Security Council circumvented the traditional use of treaties and conventions to develop broadly-agreed upon international norms under the guise of multilateralism, and essentially provided an avenue for US unilateral assertions. More honest multilateral endeavors provide the only true mechanism to foster a more holistic conception of security that seeks to protect citizens from the vastly complex threats to their human security, including those posed by the threat of terrorism.
    MALD thesis; International law
  - An International Institutionalist Approach to the Globalization of Emerging Infectious Diseases, 2005; UA015.012.DO.00103; Nieto, Andres Alejandro